<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in Christ-Church before His Excellency the Lord Deputy and the Parliament, on the fifth day of November, 1695 being the anniversary thanksgiving for the happy deliverance of K. James Ist, and the three estates of the realm of England from the most trayterous intended massacre by gun-powder : and also for the happy arrival of His present Majesty K. William on that day, for the deliverance of our church and nation / by Tobias, Lord Bishop of Dromore.</title>
            <author>Pullen, Tobias, 1648-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56272</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4195</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38013</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17161857</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17161857</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106041</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56272)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106041)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1099:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in Christ-Church before His Excellency the Lord Deputy and the Parliament, on the fifth day of November, 1695 being the anniversary thanksgiving for the happy deliverance of K. James Ist, and the three estates of the realm of England from the most trayterous intended massacre by gun-powder : and also for the happy arrival of His present Majesty K. William on that day, for the deliverance of our church and nation / by Tobias, Lord Bishop of Dromore.</title>
                  <author>Pullen, Tobias, 1648-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 19 [i.e. 17] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Norman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXVIII, 24 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, Irish --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Stuarts, 1603-1714 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106041:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106041:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED In CHRIST-CHURCH BEFORE His Excellency the Lord Deputy And the Parliament, On the Fifth day of <hi>November,</hi> 1695.</p>
            <p>BEING The Anniverſary Thankſgiving For the <hi>Happy Deliverance</hi> of K. <hi>James</hi> 1ſt, and the Three Eſtates of the Realm of <hi>England</hi> from the moſt Trayterous Intended Maſſacre by Gun-Powder:</p>
            <p>And alſo for the happy Arrival of his Preſent Majeſty K. <hi>WILLIAM</hi> on that Day, for the deliverance of our Church and Nation.</p>
            <p>By <hi>TOBIAS,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Dromore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>DUBLIN,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Norman</hi> in <hi>Dames-street,</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="resolution">
            <pb facs="tcp:106041:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Thurſday</hi> the <hi>7th</hi> of <hi>November,</hi> 1695 By the Lords Spiritual and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral in Parliament Aſſembled.</head>
            <opener>ORDERED</opener>
            <p>On motion, that the Earl of <hi>Inchiquin,</hi> and the Lord Viſcount <hi>Bleſſinton</hi> to give the Thanks of this Houſe to the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Dromore</hi> for his Sermon Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before this Houſe at <hi>Chriſt Chuch</hi> on <hi>Tueſday</hi> laſt, being the Anniverſary of the Fifth of <hi>November;</hi> and deſire his Lordſhip would pleaſe to cauſe his Sermon to be Printed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Gerard Bor. Cler. Parliamentor.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106041:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED In Chriſt-Church, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Pſalm 118. Verſe 24.</bibl>
               <q>This is the day which the Lord hath made, we will rejoyce, and be glad in it.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>'TIS a queſtion propounded by the wiſe Son of <hi>Sirach,</hi> in the 33<hi>d</hi> Chap. of <hi>Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> at the <hi>7th</hi> verſe, <hi>Why does one day excel another, when as the light of every day in the year is of the Sun? and he wiſely reſolves it in theſe following words, by the knowledge of the Lord they were diſtinguiſht, and he alter'd ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and feaſts: ſome of them has he made high days, and ſome of them has he made ordinary days: ſome of them has he bleſſed, and exalted; and ſome of them has he ſanctified, and ſet near him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For as all the works of God are full of wonder, and every one of 'em deſerves to be awfully regarded, and religiouſly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd: ſo there are ſome of 'em of a more eminent and exalted nature, and of a more rare and unuſual occurrence; and theſe remarkable works being plac't by God himſelf in a higher, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106041:3"/>
more elevated ſtation than ordinary, may therefore juſtly chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge from us men a more ſolemn honour, and a more frequent commemoration of them.</p>
            <p>And as the extraordinary manifeſtation of God's preſence to <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Buſh, did make <hi>the place whereon he ſtood to be holy ground:</hi> ſo the extraordinary marks of God's grace and favour to the Prophet <hi>David</hi> at ſome particular times and ſeaſons, did make thoſe days whereon theſe <hi>mighty works were wrought</hi> to be deſervedly eſteem'd, and devoutly obſerv'd as holy days: and 'twas ſome ſignal demonſtration of God's almighty power and goodneſs in the miraculous preſervation of <hi>David</hi>'s Perſon and Kingdom, and the utter deſtruction of his inveterate Enemies, that mov'd him ſo carefully to remind his people of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable deliverance, and ſo earneſtly to exhort 'em to a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and ſolemn Thankſgiving for ſo great a mercy, as is evident by the words of my Text; <hi>This is the day which the Lord hath made, we will rejoyce, and be glad in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are two things in the Text that plainly offer themſelves to our conſideration; Firſt, that there was ſome particular day which was made remarkable by God's extraordinary Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, in delivering King <hi>David</hi> and his people from ſome im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent danger. Secondly, that as a token of their thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for ſo ſignal a mercy, they were reſolv'd to ſolemnize that remarkable day as a day of publick and religious joy.</p>
            <p>In reference to the firſt of theſe, I ſhall inſiſt on theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Propoſitions;</p>
            <p>Firſt, that as God's mercy is over all his works: ſo his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence does more eſpecially concern it ſelf in the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of States and Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that Almighty God does more remarkably employ
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106041:3"/>
his power and goodneſs in the protection of religious States and Kingdoms <hi>profeſsing his holy and eternal Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, that there are ſome particular events that plainly diſcover the ſpecial hand of God in the management of 'em.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that it is the indiſpenſible duty of the people of God both carefully to remark, and religiouſly to celebrate the miraculous diſpenſations of Divine Providence in the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his Church. And</p>
            <p>Fifthly, that the gracious deliverance that God was pleas'd to vouchſafe theſe Nations, as on this day, has very illuſtrious marks of an extraordinary Providence impreſt upon it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſay, as God's <hi>Mercy is over all his works;</hi> ſo his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence does more eſpecially concern it ſelf in the preſervation of States and Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>Among the innumerable benefits that the planting of the Chriſtian Religion has oblig'd the world withal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the clear diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of an univerſal Providence, more eſpecially expreſt in the guidance and management of human affairs, may reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably be accounted a very conſiderable and extraordinary bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: for by the promulgation of the Goſpel we are all infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly aſſur'd, that God's Providence is extended not only to things that are moſt diſtant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and conceal'd from human view; but alſo to the moſt minute, and ſeemingly contemptible objects, and occurrences. Thus our Saviour ſpeaks to his Diſciples, <hi>Are not two ſparrows ſold for a farthing? yet not one of them does fall to th' ground without your Father:</hi> and again, he tells his diſciples in the following words, that <hi>the very hairs of their heads were all numbred:</hi> So that as nothing is ſo little as to eſcape God's Knowledge, ſo nothing is ſo deſpicable as to be diſdain'd by his Providence: For whatſoever he was pleas'd to Create
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106041:4"/>
by his power, will certainly be taken care of by his goodneſs, Yet ſince there are different degrees of excellency in the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, we may reaſonably conclude, that according to the various meaſures of their reſpective perfections, the power and mercy of Almighty God will be more or leſs concern'd in their protection and defence. Now, ſince man is the glory of the viſible World, and all things we here behold are particularly deſign'd for his benefit, and accommodation, we may aſſure our ſelves, that we are the principal objects of God's watchful eye, and that his care in the preſervation of our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and the promoting of our welfare will expreſs it ſelf in a more illuſtrous manner than in conſulting the ſafety, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of our fellow-creatures here below. And ſince the publick intereſt of States and Kingdoms is of a far greater, and momentous a concern than that of private perſons, it has been generally obſerv'd in all preceding ages from the foundation of the World, that Divine Providence has been often very emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently viſible in preventing the diſſolution of States, and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires: and accordingly we read in the Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> in the <hi>10th</hi> Chapter of his Prophecy, that God has been pleas'd to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point particular Tuteler Angels over ſeveral Countreys to manage publick affairs, and to promote the common good of their reſpective charges by inviſible ways and methods incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable by humane underſtanding: For in the <hi>13th</hi> verſe of that <hi>10th</hi> Chapter, the Angel that converſt with <hi>Daniel</hi> tells him that <hi>the Prince of the Kingdom of Perſia withſtood him one and twenty days.</hi> And the meaning of that Title of the Prince of <hi>Perſia</hi> in that Text is generally thought to be the Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian Angel of that Countrey, who, it ſeems, very diligently ſolicited the concerns of the <hi>Perſian</hi> Empire in the Court of Heaven.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That Almighty God does more remarkably imploy his power and goodneſs in the protection of Religious States, and Kingdoms, profeſſing his holy and eternal truth, is evident
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106041:4"/>
by that very tenth Chapter of the foremention'd Prophecy<hi>:</hi> for as that Tutalar Angel of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church did acquaint <hi>Daniel</hi> that the Prince of the Kingdom of <hi>Perſia</hi> had op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd him: So he aſſures him, that <hi>Michael,</hi> one of the chief Princes, came to help him. By which is meant that the <hi>Perſian</hi> Angel did ſo vigourouſly proſecute the publick in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and advantage of that Kingdom, that, were it not for the more prevalent interceſſion of <hi>Michael</hi> the Archangel, the zealous endeavours of this inferior heavenly Guardian of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation would in all probability, have been unſuccesful. From all which we may obſerve, that beſides the general Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Almighty God over all the World, he has delegated the more eſpecial care and protection of Kingdoms to Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Governors; and that he does commit the defence, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of his Church in a moſt eſpecial manner to thoſe of the higheſt order of beatified Spirits: for <hi>Michael,</hi> one of the chief Princes of the heavenly Hoſt is ſaid, in the laſt verſe of that tenth Chapter, to be <hi>Prince of the Jewiſh Nation,</hi> that is, their chiefeſt Tutelar Angel and Guardian, by which we may clearly underſtand with what honor God is pleas'd to dignify, and with what ſecurity he immures the perſons of his own Church &amp; people againſt the ſecret conſpiracies, and the forcible aſſaults of their inveterate Enemies.</p>
            <p>And that we may the more fully be aſſur'd that there is no reaſon to fear the dark deſigns, and malicious contrivances of our moſt ſubtil and potent adverſaries, God himſelf is declar'd by the Prophet <hi>David</hi> in <hi>84th Pſalm,</hi> at the <hi>11th</hi> verſe, to be <hi>a Sun</hi> and <hi>a Shield:</hi> a Sun to diſcover dark plots of our implaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble foes, and a Shield to defend us from their open violence: and ſince hell it ſelf, as <hi>Job</hi> ſays, <hi>is naked before God, and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on has no covering,</hi> we may certainly conclude that all thoſe treaſonable conſpiracies which have their riſe and original from hell, and are deſigned for the deſtruction of God's people, tho they be never ſo cunningly contriv'd, or never ſo ſecretly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106041:5"/>
carried on, will (as we have reaſon to hope) be detected, and defeated by his infinitely wiſe and over-ruling providence. For we are told by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that <hi>the fooliſhneſs of God is wiſer than men, and the weakneſs of God is ſtronger than men:</hi> that is, the leaſt degree, if I may ſo ſpeak, of Divine Power can baffle the utmoſt ſtrength of the greateſt Princes: and the leaſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of divine wiſdom can infatuate the beſt laid deſigns of the moſt ſubtil Politicians.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I ſay that there are ſome particular diſpenſations that plainly diſcover the ſpecial hand of God in the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of 'em. For tho the works of divine providence be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly cloudy &amp; dark, yet there are ſome particular events that have the ſignatures of God's Power, Wiſdom and Goodneſs ſo plainly ſtampt upon 'em, and are of ſuch peculiar frame and make, that all men that ſeriouſly conſider 'em ſhall ſay, <hi>This has God done, for they ſhall perceive that it is his Work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in reference to theſe unuſual occurrences, there are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Phraſes in the holy Scriptures which are very obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, and particularly import the variety of God's methods in theſe extraordinary diſpenſations of his providence. Thus God's arm is ſometimes expreſt in holy Scipture, to be made bare, and to be lifted up, in the atchievement of ſome prodigious Works. An example of the firſt of theſe we have in the 52<hi>d</hi> Chapter of the Prophecy of <hi>Iſaih,</hi> at the <hi>10th</hi> verſe: Where the Prophet, reminding the Church of the great miracles which the Lord had wrought for her ſafety and advantage, ſays <hi>That the Lord has had made bare his holy arm in the eyes of all the Nations:</hi> that is, as a Souldier in the heat of battle will diſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage his hands from whatever may hinder, him in the uſe of his Sword, and if he find his Gantlet heavy, and cumberſom to him, will quit it to enjoy the natural ſtrength, and freedom of his arm, So when God ſees his Church and People in immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent danger of periſhing, if they be left to the natural efficacy
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106041:5"/>
of viſible cauſes, He is frequently pleas'd in ſuch an extraordinary exigence openly to appear in their behalf, and laying aſide ſome weak and feeble inſtrument, wherein his hand did inviſibly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage it ſelf in their defence, he <hi>makes bare his Arm in the Eyes of all the Nations,</hi> He delivers them from the prevailing Force of their Enemies by ſome miraculous inſtances of this infinite power, and love.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Another Phraſe made uſe of in holy Scripture to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the ſpecial Providence of Almighty God in ſome particular emergencies, is, the raiſing and lifting up of his Arm. Thus in the 26 Chapter of the Prophecy of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> at the 11 Verſe, the Prophet Addreſſes himſelf to God in theſe words; <hi>Lord when thy Hand is lifted up they will not ſee, but they ſhall ſee and be aſhamed for their envy at the People.</hi> Now by his Hand being lifted up we muſt not underſtand Gods acting purely by his own Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potence, without the concurrence of any viſible aſſiſtant; but only that he raiſes, and exalts cauſes to ſo great a degree of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as to enable 'em to perform ſuch actions as are vaſtly beyond the ſmall proportion of their Natural ſtrength.</p>
            <p>In this ſenſe we muſt underſtand the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Conqueſts of the Land of <hi>Canaan:</hi> for God himſelf do's frequently tell 'em, that the Nations whoſe Land they ſhould poſſeſs, were <hi>ſtronger, and mightier than they;</hi> and yet he Commands 'em not to be diſmay'd, becauſe the <hi>Lord himſelf ſhould go before 'em, and ſhould deſtroy their Enemies with a great deſtruction until they were Conſum'd.</hi> By all which promiſes the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did not apprehend, that God would put them into the quiet Poſſeſſion of the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> without a neceſſity of their own Fighting; but that he would bleſs their Arms with wonderful ſucceſs, and would enable 'em to the gaining of thoſe Victories which they never would have got, but by the aſſiſtance of his Almighty Power.</p>
            <p>But Fourthly, It is the indiſpenſible Duty of the People of God,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106041:6"/>
both carefully to Remark, and Religiouſly to celebrate the Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous diſpenſations of Divine Providence in the preſervation of his Church. Among the ſeveral notes of diſtinction betwixt ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Creatures, and brute Beaſts, this is reckon'd as one of the moſt conſiderable, that whereas brute Beaſts do only Stare at ſome unuſual objects, and are ſtartl'd at ſome ſudden and ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing accidents; God has been pleas'd to endue Mankind with the power of Reaſoning, ſo that they do not barely perceive the things that are Repreſented to 'em by their ſenſes, but alſo can narrowly prey, and ſtrictly ſearch into the Reaſons of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions, and I may juſtly ſay, there is as great a diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the natural Man, and the ſpiritually minded Chriſtian, in reference to ſome ſignal events in humane Life, and remarkable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Divine Providence.</p>
            <p>For the moſt earleſs &amp; inconſiderate Sinner cannot but be amaz'd at ſome ſudden &amp; unexpected changes in a Kingdom, and may take ſuch notice of 'em, as to make 'em the ſubject of his Diſcourſe, and the entertainment of his idle hours; but if he goes no further than a ſlight and ſuperficial conſideration of 'em; if he do's not ſtrictly enquire, and diligently ſearch into the ſecret ſprings of theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary motions, he not only fruſtrates the good and wiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of Divine providence in thoſe wonderful Revolutions, but does alſo affront his own rational Faculties: he debates the Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his Nature, and ſinks himſelf into the low and ignoble rank of <hi>the Beaſts that periſh.</hi> Whereas on the contrary, the Faithful Servants of Almighty God, do not only plainl, perceive, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Remark, but do alſo Religiouſly admire, highly extol, and humbly adore his infinite Wiſdom, Power and Goodneſs in theſe ſurprizing and miraculous Events.</p>
            <p>A Remarkable inſtance of both theſe different Tempers we have Recorded in the 92 <hi>Pſalm,</hi> where the Prophet having declar'd at the 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Verſe, <hi>that the Lord had made him glad through his work,</hi> and that he would <hi>Triumph in the works of his Hand,</hi> and in an extacy
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106041:6"/>
broke out, at the 5 Verſe in theſe words, <hi>O Lord how great are thy Works? Thy thoughts are very deep,</hi> he aſſures us in the next Verſe, <hi>that a brutiſh Man knows not, neither does a fool underſtand this.</hi> And elſewhere the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> gives it as the Character of wicked Men, that <hi>they regard not in their minds the Works of God! nor the operation of his Hands,</hi> tho they be never ſo Signal in their own Nature, and never ſo rare, and unuſual in their Event; and of this ſort was that wonderful Deliverance which we ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Commemorate on this Day, which brings me to the,</p>
            <p>Fifth Particular, <hi>That the Gracious Deliverance that God was pleas'd to Vouchſafe theſe Nations as on this Day has very illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Marks of an extraordinary Providence impreſt on it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of theſe I might mention many, but I ſhall inſiſt only on Two: the Firſt of which is the critical timing and ſeaſonableneſs of this Gracious Deliverance, which was wrought for us in the Gate of Death, and the very minute almoſt of our deſign'd Deſtruction. And indeed 'tis the uſual method of Divine Providence intirely to Baffle the deſigns of the Wicked, when they are in the heighth of all their hopes and ſuddenly to throw 'em down from the top and pinacle of their Towring expectations.</p>
            <p>God might very eaſily; if he pleas'd, defeat the bloody purpoſes of ungodly Men in the Firſt conception of 'em in their minds, and ſtifle 'em in the Firſt inſtant of their motions; but he looks upon it as more agreeable to the Excellent deſigns of his infinite Wiſdom, and Goodneſs; and to the manifeſtation of his Almighty Power, to permit their Fancies to be impregnated with the Vain hope of a happy ſucceſs in their ungodly project: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuddenly, and ſurprizingly makes the iſſue of their wicked Hearts abortive, and when the Children of iniquity are juſt <hi>come to the Birth,</hi> he does not permit 'em to have <hi>ſtrength to bring forth,</hi> and grants his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple a wonderful Deliverance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> falling down the Precipice of utter Ruine and Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:106041:7"/>
Thus in the Paſſage of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> over the River <hi>Jordan,</hi> we read that <hi>as ſoon as the Prieſts that bare the Ark were come to</hi> Jordan, and <hi>their Feet were dipt in the brim of the Water,</hi> and they might according to the meaſure of Humane reaſon have expected at the next ſtep, to be Swallowed up in the deep, the Text ſays, that <hi>the Waters fail'd and were cut off,</hi> and that Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver which juſt before had overflow'd his Banks, did then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake his Channel; and <hi>the People paſſed over on dry Ground.</hi> We ſee in this Inſtance that the time which God Appointed for the Paſſage of his People over <hi>Jordan</hi> was at that time of the Year when his Flood was at the heighth; and we alſo ſee that the Waters were not cut off till the <hi>Feet of the Prieſts were wet in the brim of the River;</hi> and then, and not tell then it was that the Text tells us that <hi>the Waters which came down from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, ſtood and roſe up upon a heap. And the Prieſts that bare the Ark of the Covenant of the Lord ſtood firm on dry ground in the midſt of</hi> Jordan, as we may read in the third Chapter of <hi>Joſhua</hi> at the two laſt Verſes.</p>
            <p>And of the like nature was the Deliverance wrought for us as on this Day<hi>:</hi> for while our Enemies had made the Cellers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Parliament Houſe a Tophet, according to the Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it in the thirteenth Chapter of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> at the laſt Verſe; <hi>Tho' it was prepared for the King,</hi> and the three Eſtates of the Realm; tho' the <hi>Pile thereof was Fire and much Wood,</hi> yet the latter part of the <hi>Character</hi> of <hi>Tophet</hi> was wanting; <hi>for the breath of the Lord</hi> was ſo far unlike a <hi>ſtream of Brimſtone to enkindle it,</hi> that like <hi>a ſtream of many Waters</hi> it prevented the breaking out of the unconquerable Flame.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>18th</hi> Chapter of the Wiſdom of <hi>Solomon,</hi> we have a moſt Excellent Idea given us of Gods ſurprizing Vengeance on the Enemies of his Church in the ſudden and unexpected de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the firſt born among the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> in theſe moſt remarkable Words, <hi>While all things were in quiet ſilence, and that</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:106041:7"/>
               <hi>night was in the midſt of her ſwift courſe, thine Almighty Word lept down from Heaven out of thy Royal Throne, as a fierce Man of War into the midſt of a Land of Deſtruction, and brought thy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feign'd Commandment as a ſharp ſword, and ſtanding up, fill'd all things with Death, and touched the Heaven, but it ſtood upon the Earth.</hi> Theſe words may with a little alteration very clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſcribe to us the ſurprizing Wonders of this days Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, for while the miſchievous, and fatal Plots of our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were <hi>in quiet ſilence,</hi> and in full ſecurity of Succeſs; and while their mighty Works of helliſh Darkneſs were not only <hi>in the midſt of their ſwift Courſe,</hi> but juſt brought to the point of Execution, then it was that <hi>Gods Almighty Word leapt down from Heaven, out of</hi> his <hi>Royal Throne,</hi> to ſave his People, as he did formerly to deſtroy his Enemies, <hi>and brought</hi> Gods ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs <hi>Command as a ſharp Word,</hi> to cut off the implacable Foes of the publick Peace, and the Proteſtant Religion: <hi>It touched the Heaven, and ſtood upon the Earth,</hi> it had its Commiſſion from above, very clearly to diſcover, and effectually to prevent that unparallel'd Maſſacre here below, which was juſt ready to be executed upon us; ſo that, we <hi>were as Firebrands ſnatcht out of</hi> that vaſt and univerſal <hi>Burning,</hi> deſign'd upon the whole Nation, in the very critical moment of extream Danger.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Mark and Character of Gods ſpecial Providence, is the great Benefit, and advantage of ſome particular events, for the defence of Truth, the ſupport of Religion, and increaſe of Pienty. God who deliver'd his People out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> would not deſtroy 'em in the Wilderneſs; much leſs in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> into which he had miraculouſly brought them; and ſince the ſame God had deliver'd us from more than Aegyptian Darkneſs, under the Blindneſs and Superſtitions of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and from more then Aegyptian Servitude, under the cruel Tyranny of the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> and had alſo brought us into <hi>Canaan</hi> into a Land ſlowing with Milk and Honey, where we have been plentifully fed with <hi>the Milk of Gods word, and had</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:106041:8"/>
               <hi>toſted of the Heavenly gift,</hi> the Hony of celeſtial Ordinances; we had no reaſon but to reſt aſſur'd of his ever watchful Care and Providence over us in our preſervation.</p>
            <p>And as God was pleas'd as on this Day plainly to diſcover the works of Darkneſs, and miraculouſly to prevent the Execution of 'em; and has ſucceſsfully compleated a Deliverance for his People no leſs ſignal and illuſtrious than the former<hi>:</hi> the Firſt Plot indeed was deſign'd to blow up the Parliament-Houſe and the three Eſtates of the Realm, but this late deſign was formed againſt, and if it had taken Effect, would have entirely deſtroyed the very Conſtitution of Parliaments, and have rooted up the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Original Foundations of our Government.</p>
            <p>The firſt Conſpiracy as Conſcious of its own Guilt did hide its face in the darkneſs of the night, in the receſſes of Vaults and the privacy of ſecret Conſults, but in this late Conſpiracy Popiſh Villany appeared in open View, our deſtruction was not privately deſign'd, nor carefully conceal'd from our knowledg, but openly avow'd, publickly manag'd, and Triumphantly boaſted of.</p>
            <p>Our Land brought forth not only Frogs, but venemous Toads even in our Kings chambers, &amp; which is worſt of all, this grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous plague of Egypt was thought by ſome the greateſt bleſſing of the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and it was Gods Infinite Mercy to us that our Rivers were not turned into Blood, which his preſent Majeſty's timely landing, as on this day, did very happily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent<hi>:</hi> and as on this memorable day God had formerly preſerved us from utter ruin and deſtruction deſigned us by the whole Power and Force of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo having employed his preſent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty in the late mighty work of our deliverance, He was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to give him a remarkable omen of his future good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs by Landing him in <hi>England</hi> as on this day. For then it was that Superſtition and Idolatry appeared with open Face, and were violently bearing down all before 'em; then it was that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106041:8"/>
the <hi>Egyptian</hi> darkneſs of Popery was overſpreading theſe three Nations, and more then <hi>Egyptian</hi> ſlavery was very cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attending it. Then it was that our Rights both Civil and Eccleſiaſtical were invaded, and whoever wou'd not Worſhip the Images that were then ſet up, was in great danger of being Puniſh'd as the three Children were, whom we read of in the Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> for the Fire which was of old prepar'd for Hereticks and had been for ſo many Ages kept alive, and was but lately extinguiſhed by Aboliſhing the Writ <hi>de Haeretico Comburendo,</hi> was enkindling again, but now the Embers are ſo effectually quencht by a ſuddain and wonderful Rain from Heaven, that there is no fear of a Future revival of the Flame.</p>
            <p>We read in the 18th <hi>Chap.</hi> of the firſt Book of the <hi>Kings,</hi> that when the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were mightily diſtreſſed by the extremity of Famine, <hi>Elijah went up to the top of</hi> Carmel, <hi>and caſt himſelf down upon the Earth,</hi> and Commanded his Servant to <hi>look toward the Sea ſeven times,</hi> and 'tis ſaid, that <hi>at the ſeventh time he ſaw a cloud riſe out of the Sea like a Mans hand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> which afterward overſpread the whole Firmament, and became the ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and effectual means of reſtoring their former plenty and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity; and truly the circumſtances of our late Affairs, both in Church and State, had much the ſame diſmal proſpect with that of the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the time of Famine; for when ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral years we had Groan'd under the grievous burthen of Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary power, when we had many times <hi>caſt our ſelves down upon the Earth at the Footſtool of the Throne of Grace,</hi> when we had often humbly Proſtrated our Souls and Bodies before God, and had look't often towards the Sea for our Relief then it was that we at laſt perceiv'd a Cloud ariſing out of the Sea, and encreaſing daily, till in a little time, it overſpread the Firmament, and then God was pleas'd to <hi>ſend a Gracious Rain upon his Inheritance, and to refreſh it when it was weary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:106041:9"/>
And one ſignal inſtance of Gods avenging Hand, on the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable Enemies of the Proteſtant Religion, was the impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing on their guilty Minds, ſuch timorous Miſgivings, and foreboding apprehenſions of the approaching Period of their Power and Greatneſs, as made their hearts faint, and their hands Weak and Trembling; ſo that, the joints of their Loyns were loos'd, and their knees ſmote one againſt a nother, and what we read in the fourteenth Chapter of the firſt Book of <hi>Samuel,</hi> concerning the Miraculous Succeſs of <hi>Jonathan</hi> and his Armour Bearer, was almoſt fulfill'd in our Days<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for there was a trembling <hi>in the Hoſt</hi> of the Enemies of Gods Church, the <hi>Garriſon</hi> and the <hi>Spoylers</hi> they alſo <hi>trembled;</hi> ſo that, <hi>it was a very great Trembling, and behold the Multitude melted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, ſince ſo Gracious a Deliverance has been wrought for us, ſince in the wonderful <hi>Year of</hi> 88, we ſaw a truly <hi>invincible Armada</hi> making towards our Coaſts, and ſince that auſpicious Wind which happily brought our moſt Gracious Deliverer to our Lands has effectually freed 'em of thoſe ſwarms of Forreign <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts</hi> with which our <hi>Canaan</hi> like <hi>Egypt</hi> has been lately ſo miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably infeſted, and has <hi>thrown 'em into the Sea;</hi> ſince our Judges are Reſtor'd as at the firſt, and our Counſellors as at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and we are all compas'd about with the Bleſſings of Peace and good Government; What now Remains, but that our Return of Thankfulneſs to Almighty God, be in ſome Regard ſuitable to the greatneſs of his Mercies, and as our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance has been as Signal and Remarkable as that of King <hi>David</hi>'s and his People, ſo our Gratitude to our Gracious and Almighty Preſerver, ſhould be as Publick and Solemn, as Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Affectionate as theirs; which brings me to the ſecond particular in my Text. Viz. that King David and his People were reſolved to ſolemnize the remarkable day of their Deliverance as a Day of Publick and Religious joy, which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in theſe Words, <hi>we will rejoyce and be glad in it,</hi> but
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106041:9"/>
having ſpent ſo much time in diſcourſing on the firſt Head; I ſhall <hi>only mention</hi> ſome few duties which theſe words import, and leave the enlargement on 'em to your own me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation; and the</p>
            <p>Firſt one of thoſe duties which the latter part of my Text im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plys, and which this days ſolemnity obliges us to perform, is a publick and religious thankfulneſs to Almighty God for ſo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral and ſo miraculous a preſervation; for 'tis very evident, that <hi>Rome</hi> intended, as on this day, to treat the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> united in one body in Parliament, as <hi>Caligula</hi> deſign'd to treat <hi>Rome</hi> her ſelf; <hi>If it had but one neck, to cut it off at a ſtroke,</hi> to deſtroy it at once with a mighty deſtruction. For all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives of the Realm, as the Office of the day expreſſes, <hi>were by Popiſh Treachery appointed as ſheep to the ſlaughter, in a moſt barbarous and ſavage manner, beyond the example of former ages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But God has been graciouſly pleas'd both by his wiſdom to detect, and by his power to blaſt this inhuman Conſpiracy; and therefore we are all indiſpenſibly oblig'd to take care, that the religious expreſſions of our gratitude for ſo great a Bleſſing, may on the wings of Praiſe and Thankſgiving aſcend to Heaven, from whence this wonderful deliverance came. And</p>
            <p>Secondly, our publick Thankfulneſs for ſo ſignal a Mercy, ſhould expreſs it ſelf in eminent acts of Charity to the Poor: for as the miraculous preſervation of us, as on this day, from this inhuman Plot of our Popiſh Enemies, does highly reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the wonderful deliverance of the Jews from the mercileſs deſigns of <hi>Haman;</hi> ſo we ought to imitate the remarkable Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of their Benevolence on the <hi>Feaſt of Purim,</hi> in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous diſtribution of our Alms to our indigent Brethren; as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106041:10"/>
we find it recorded at the firſt Inſtitution of that Feaſt, in the <hi>9th</hi> Chapter of <hi>Eſther,</hi> at the 22<hi>d</hi> verſe: where 'tis ſaid, that <hi>the days wherein the Jews reſted from their Enemies, and the month which was turned unto them from mourning to joy, they ſhould make days of Feaſting, and Joy, and of ſending portions one to another, and gifts to the poor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But laſtly, our miraculous deliverance, as on this day, ſhou'd work in us all a hearty repentance for our paſt offences, and a thorough reformation of our lives for the time to come; and as we expreſs our publick ſenſe of this mighty Bleſſing by our publick Offices of religious Praiſe, and as by our Charity we declare our gratitude to Almighty God, by making our poor diſtreſſed Brethren here below partakers of our Joy, ſo by a true and ſincere contrition, we ſhou'd extend our Joy to the triumphant Saints above, and cauſe <hi>joy in the preſence of the Angels of God over</hi> ſo many <hi>penitent Sinners.</hi> And this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent duty of a general Repentance on ſo extraordinary an occaſion, I ſhall re-inforce upon you in the words of <hi>Samuel</hi> to the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in the <hi>12th</hi> Chap. of the firſt Book of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel,</hi> at the <hi>24th</hi> verſe; <hi>Fear the Lord, and ſerve him in truth with all your heart; for conſider how great things he has done for you;</hi> and then we may with a rational confidence of future ſafety, commit our ſelves, and all our private and publick af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, our Perſons, and our Relatives, our Religion and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to the care and protection of Divine Providence, being fully aſſur'd, that God's infinite Goodneſs will prevent the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, his Wiſdom will infatuate the Councels, and his Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs will quell the Power of our moſt formidable Enemies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for Omnipotence is able to ſupport us, and Infinite Mercy will never be unwilling to help us, and Omniſcience can never be Forgetful of us, and 'tis impoſſible for Truth it ſelf to diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:106041:10"/>
And now, ſince God <hi>has deliver'd us from ſo great a Death, and does deliver,</hi> in him <hi>we'll hope that he will yet deliver us;</hi> and that he will compleat his wonderful mercy to us, by the ſpeedy converſion of the Corrigible, and the utter confuſion of our implacable Enemies: Which God of his Infinite Mercy grant, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
